Guide to the Hughes-Gray Family Papers, 1805-1926 RL.00588
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hughes-Gray Family papers
1805-1926
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hughes-Gray family
RL.00588
3.6 Linear Feet
Family with publishing connections in Maryland. Ezekiel Hughes was editor of the HERALD in Frederick, Maryland. Jeremiah Hughes owned the NILES NATIONAL REGISTER, and other publishing concerns. Principally correspondence of the Hughes and Gray familes of Baltimore, Annapolis, and Frederick, Md. Pervasive topics include personal and family matters, Md. and national politics, and religion. Topics occurring less frequently include finances related to the publishing business and the marketing of volumes, the Civil War, city missions for the poor, dealings with Native Americans, and Communism. The collection also includes 31 volumes of notes and diaries compiled by Ellis Hughes, chief anatomist at the University of Md., over the period of roughly 1830-1865. His 1865 diary makes reference to Lincoln's assassination and the capture of Jefferson Davis. The remaining five volumes were compiled by Jeremiah's daughter Susanna Hughes, who herself entertained literary aspirations. These volumes are a mixture of diary, devotional, literary copybook, scrapbook, and original composition.
1,114 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Hughes-Gray Family Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase from 1975-1978.
Biographical Note
The Hughes and Gray families had publishing connections in Maryland. Ezekiel Hughes was editor of the HERALD in Frederick, Maryland. Jeremiah Hughes owned the NILES NATIONAL REGISTER, and other publishing concerns.
Collection Overview
Principally correspondence of the Hughes and Gray familes of Baltimore, Annapolis, and Frederick, Md. Pervasive topics include personal and family matters, Md. and national politics, and religion. Topics occurring less frequently include finances related to the publishing business and the marketing of volumes, the Civil War, city missions for the poor, dealings with Native Americans, and Communism. The collection also includes 31 volumes of notes and diaries compiled by Ellis Hughes, chief anatomist at the University of Maryland, over the period of roughly 1830-1865. His 1865 diary makes reference to Lincoln's assassination and the capture of Jefferson Davis. The remaining five volumes were compiled by Jeremiah's daughter Susanna Hughes, who herself entertained literary aspirations. These volumes are a mixture of diary, devotional, literary copybook, scrapbook, and original composition.
Indians, Treatment of -- North America; Maryland -- Politics and government; City missions -- United States; Church work with the poor -- United States; Publishers and publishing -- History; Religion -- History -- 19th century; Davis, Jefferson, 1808-1889 -- Captivity, 1865-1867; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865 -- Assassination; Communism; Gray family; Hughes family; Hughes-Gray family; Hughes, Ellis
- Hughes-Gray Family Papers, 1805-1926, 9 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Collections contains 31 journals of Ellis Hughes. In Box 6, journals cover President Abraham Lincoln's assassination and funeral, the capture of Jefferson Davis, and other American Civil War events.
  - Correspondence, 1815-1843 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1844-1857 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1858-1879 Aug. (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1879 Sept.-1887 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1888 (Box 5)
  - Writings, 1805-1917 (Box 6)
  - Legal papers (Box 6)
  - Financial papers (Box 6)
  - Journals, 1845-1864, 7 volumes (Box 6)
  - Morality speeches (Box 6)
  - Journals, 1839 and undated, 6 volumes (Box 7)
  - Journals, 1832-1852, 7 volumes (Box 8)
  - Notebook, 1846 (Box 8)
  - Journals, 1846-1852, 14 volumes (Box 9)